(low music throughout)
What is alternative text?
Alternative text, also known as "alt text,"
is descriptive text that conveys
the meaning of an image in digital content.
It's designed to make visual content accessible
to people with vision disabilities.
While there are other benefits of alt text
for all users, this video focuses
on people who use screen readers.
When a person uses a screen reader,
the screen reader will read the on-screen text aloud
using text-to-speech technology.
When the screen reader reaches an image,
it will announce that it has detected an image
and read the alt text for that image
so the user can know what the image
is meant to convey.
Without alt text, people who use screen readers
cannot access the information
provided in the images.
This is why alt text is a requirement
in the Section 508 Standards
for creating digital content.
Different authoring tools will have
different ways of adding alt text.
For example, to add alt text to an image
in Microsoft Word, open the contextual menu,
or right-click menu, of the image.
Next, select "View Alt Text,"
then enter text that appropriately describes
the image and communicates its purpose.
When writing alt text, follow these guidelines
to ensure the text is as helpful
and meaningful as possible.
(whoosh)
If an image is only decorative,
and does not convey meaningful information,
set the alt text as decorative so that screen readers
recognize that the image does not need
to be announced and can be skipped.
In Microsoft Word, you can do this
by viewing the alt text and checking the box
that says, "Mark as decorative."
Any program you use should also have
its own specific guidance on how to do this.
(whoosh)
Avoid using default or AI-generated alt text,
since these descriptions usually
do not communicate the actual purpose
of the image. For example,
an AI may describe a screenshot of a form
as "screenshot of a phone screen."
However, if the image is intended to show
how to use the form, the alt text will need
to describe the content of the screenshot
to make the description meaningful.
(whoosh)
If you have an image or logo
that contains text, make sure the alt text
repeats that text word for word.
For example, for this logo of section508.gov,
the alt text says, "GSA logo with text.
"section508 dot gov.
"Buy. Build. Be accessible."
(whoosh)
Keep your descriptions short and focused
on the purpose of the image.
Avoid repeating information
that is already in the main text,
and don't use unnecessary phrases like,
"this is a photo of," or descriptions
of irrelevant details in the image.
For example, if your image is designed
to show how a ramp helps wheelchair users,
you do not need to include an in-depth
description of the wheelchair user's clothes
or physical appearance in your alt text.
(whoosh)
For more guidance on alt text and accessibility,
visit the resources for content creators
on section508.gov.
This video is a product
of the General Services Administration.